This is it.
做好了
This…
这样…
will make it…
就能形成…
into the shape of fire.
火的形状
You really like that.
真不错呢
A miniature bonfire.
迷你版的篝火
Please enjoy.
请慢用
SCOTT JOPLIN
（斯科特·乔普林）
Did you officially stamp it?
已经正式盖章了吗？
Yes…
是啊
my kids were taken too.
孩子也被带走了
When you gaze at this fire,
像这样凝视着火焰
don't you feel as if you're being left behind in time?
会有种陷入时间里停滞不前的感觉呢
An escape from reality.
那是逃避现实
Should I…
不如…
quit being a doctor?
我把医生这份工作辞掉好了
That again.
又说这个
500 ML
（500毫升）
NURSE STATION
（护士站）
Watching it slowly burn is quite boring.
看着它慢慢燃烧也满无聊的
ETIZOLAM
（镇静剂 依替唑仑）
You told him?
你告诉他了？
I did.
没错
I told him that he's got three months left.
我跟他说了只剩三个月
Why?
为什么啊？
I was going to tell him.
我想亲口跟他说的
But you weren't telling him.
但你一直没说啊
Or perhaps you can't.
应该是说不出口吧
Is it even necessary
真的有必要
to tell people how much time they have left?
告知患者他们还剩多少时间吗？
Good work today, Mr. Naruse.
成濑先生 辛苦你了
Yes.
是啊
How are you feeling today?
今天身体感觉如何？
I'm doing okay.
还好吧
I see.
这样啊
-I'll open the door. -Thank you very much.
-我来开门 -谢谢
Pardon us. We're coming in.
我们进去了
Excuse me.
不好意思
Hello.
你们好
Let's turn here.
要转弯啰
Heave-ho.
哎哟
Here we go.
好了
Would you like a blanket?
要盖被子吗？
You're playing a crossword puzzle?
你在玩填字游戏啊？
Yeah.
是啊
CROSSWORD PUZZLE
（填字游戏）
I'll excuse myself.
那我先去忙了
Chat…
聊天…
Cha-, Cha-, Cha-, GP…
聊天…聊天机器…
That's not right.
不对啊
Pardon me.
打扰了
Mr. Naruse, how are you feeling?
成濑先生 感觉怎么样啊？
At least knock before coming in.
进来之前至少敲个门嘛
It's a curtain.
这是窗帘耶
You're finally here, Dr. Youngster.
你总算来了 小伙子医生
"Dr. Youngster".
“小伙子医生”
Quit calling me that.
别再那样叫我啦
If you can joke around, you must be fine…
还能开玩笑的话 你应该…
or not.
不太好呢
I can't take painkillers yet.
还不能用止痛药
It's only been two hours.
两小时前才注射过
Then, maybe we can use a stabilizer.
那 不然用稳定剂吧
Nothing can help this amount of pain.
这种程度的疼痛用什么药都没用
Doctor,
佐仓医生
I can't help how bad it hurts.
痛得我快受不了了
Yes.
是
Whenever I can bear it,
没那么痛的时候
I only stare at the ceiling.
我也只能盯着天花板
Right.
是
Why am I alive?
我为什么还活着呢？
Doctor,
佐仓医生
have you ever spent a day staring at the ceiling?
你有试过一整天只盯着天花板吗？
Yes.
有
Huh?
什么？
To understand the lives
为了了解卧病在床、无法起身的患者
of my patients who can't get up from bed,
是如何过日子的
I spent one of my days off lying on the sofa
我曾在休息日的时候 一整天躺在沙发上
for a full 24 hours without moving once.
躺了整整24小时
Not for the bathroom?
厕所也没去？
I wore a diaper.
我穿了尿不湿
-Seriously? -Yes.
-真的假的？ -真的
I couldn't use a feeding tube,
不过 我没办法用喂食管
so, I just kept a Vitamin Jelly next to me.
所以只能准备好维他命果冻
I just thought it was incredibly difficult.
我当时满脑子都在想 “这简直太难受了啊”
You're amazing, Doctor.
你好厉害啊 佐仓医生
Somehow…
真的…
I just had the time.
我只是太闲了
Doctor, I've heard how much time I have left.
佐仓医生 他们跟我说了我还剩多少时间了
Yes.
是
I've heard.
我知道
From Mr. Komiya.
小宫医生告诉我了
Won't you just kill me?
不如你直接杀了我吧
It's spread from my colon to my liver.
从大肠一路扩散到肝脏
How many years has it been?
都多少年了？
I've gone through so many operations and medicines.
动过无数次手术 用过那么多药物
There's no point in living just to suffer.
活着只是在受苦而已 一点意义也没有
It'll only get worse from here.
接下来只会更糟糕
I'm scared, and I want to die.
我好害怕 好想死
Okay.
好啊
I can
就这么办吧
accept that.
我帮你
Really?
真的吗？
Yes.
是的
You're my Lucky Seventh.
你是我的幸运七呢
Ever since I joined internal medicine,
自从我被调到内科
I've heard people tell me, "Doctor, I've had enough."
我一直都想辞职不干了
You're the seventh person
你是第七个
to tell me that they want to die.
跟我说自己不想活了 想要结束生命的患者
I can't move. I'm bedridden.
因为一直下不了床吗？
Some people die of the pain.
也有死于剧烈疼痛的
Only five minutes with potassium.
注射钾的话 五分钟就好了
If we first administer Propofol,
只要事先注射丙泊酚
it can be just like falling asleep.
就能像入睡那样离开
Is that potassium…
钾这种东西…
available immediately?
马上就能拿到手吗？
Not immediately, but we can get it.
需要一点时间 但没问题
It's in our medicine storage.
医疗用品室那里就有
Mr. Naruse,
成濑先生
won't you try to live?
可是啊 你不想活下去吗？
Won't you try to live before you die?
在死之前 好好活一次？
Before you die…
在死之前…
won't you live?
好好活一次？
You measured 75/115.
血压115/75
"Ten things to do before I die."
“死前要做的十件事”
That Youngster Doctor told me to write it today.
小伙子医生叫我今天要写好这个
"Live before you die."
他说：“在死之前 好好活一次”
What is this, some teen movie?
以为自己在拍青春电影啊？
Thank you very much.
谢谢你
Youngster.
“小伙子”
Oh, that must be Doctor Sakura.
是佐仓医生吧
I secretly think of him as a lifelong teenager.
其实我都偷偷在心里 把他称为“永远的中二病”
Do you like him?
你喜欢他喔？
Huh?
什么？
Hit the mark.
被我说中了
Stop that!
别乱说啦
-A forbidden love. -Hey.
-是禁忌的爱恋啊 -够咯
"Ten things to do before I die."
“死前要做的十件事”
I want to do a quadruple jump.
我想完成一次四周跳
Like Yuzuru Hanyu.
像羽生结弦那样
I can't think of anything.
我没什么想做的啊
Even if you ask me, there's nothing.
即使这样问我 我也想不出来
I'm just scared.
我只觉得好害怕
I'm kidding. Don't make that face.
开玩笑的啦 别摆出那种表情嘛
How's it looking?
情况如何？
Welcome back.
你来了
Huh? It's blank.
咦？什么都没写嘛
You see,
我说你啊
you watch too many stupid movies.
看太多不切实际的电影了
Those movies
那些电影情节
with a dog that jumps in the water and saves his owner
不是狗狗为了救主人 奋不顾身跳进河里
or patients with only a few months to live hits it big.
就是只剩几个月可活的病患 突然发大财什么的
I thought we could at least check off your bucket list.
我想说至少可以实现你的心愿嘛
This isn't something worth writing out, but…
倒是有件不怎么值得写下来的事…
Yes?
什么事？
Don't you have pictures hanging around here?
这医院墙上不是都挂着画吗？
Those pictures don't move.
那些画都不会动呢
And the windows only open an inch.
窗户也只能打开一点点
So that no one jumps out.
避免有人从窗户跳楼
You don't need to say all that.
说这些干嘛啦？
We can't feel the wind here.
所以这里面都感受不到风
Although it's windy somewhere,
明明某处有风在吹
I could never feel it.
我却感受不到
I may want to feel the breeze again.
好想再感受一次风的气息啊
Please hop on.
上来吧
Hang on tight.
抓紧啰 抱紧我
-You got it. -Hey!
-抓紧了 -不是…
Wait, wait, wait, that's too much.
等等…不是这样抓啦
-That's dangerous. -Let's go.
-这样很危险耶 -出发
KANTO GENERAL HOSPITAL
（关东综合医院）
That's dangerous.
这样很危险
Quit it!
好了啦
Seriously.
真是的
It feels good.
真舒服
We've come pretty far.
我们骑很远了呢
That's dangerous.
等一下 危险啦
Don't do that!
都说很危险了
That's dangerous!
真是的
-Are you okay? -Yeah.
-你还好吗？ -嗯
My legs are all cramped.
腿都快抽筋了
I'm beat.
好累喔
That seems good.
应该可以了
Here you go.
来 请享用
Wow.
哇
-It's hot! -Yeah, it's hot.
-好烫 -小心烫喔
It's been a while.
好久没吃那么烫的食物了
Delicious.
好好吃
This sausage is great.
维也纳香肠超好吃
Eating is life.
这样吃东西才是活着
That's not to say hospital food is killing me,
医院餐不至于要我的命
but it's just sad.
但就是令人心酸
Hot, hot, hot!
好烫…
So hot!
好烫
Please be careful.
小心烫喔
Yeah.
好
Mr. Naruse is temporarily discharged,
成濑先生暂时出院
and Mr. Sakura has resigned.
而佐仓医生辞职了
No, I still have his resignation letter.
不 他的离职信还在我这里
I'll tell the board chairman that he's taking a day off.
我会跟理事长说他要休假一天
Besides, isn't that guy still going to a mental hospital?
那家伙有在看心理咨商吧？
Right, only just after the incident.
那件事发生后不久有去过
He's not going anymore.
现在应该没去了
So, they're just out on a trip?
所以他们俩去旅行了？
Yes.
是的
I received this from them.
他们给我发了这个
Looks like they're having fun.
看来玩得很开心呢
-Whoa! -Oh, no!
-哎呀！ -怎么啦？
Mr. Naruse, be careful!
成濑先生 小心一点啦
Be careful.
小心一点
Let's go!
来
Wow.
哇
I've never seen this.
还有这种玩意儿啊？
Isn't it cool?
很有趣吧？
It's like the fire is trying to keep living.
这火苗就像在拼命生存一样
Huh?
什么？
Just as it starts to fade,
每次快要熄灭的时候
each time,
它又会…
it changes shape and burns on.
换个形状继续燃烧
It looks to me as if it's desperately trying to stay alive.
看起来就像是拼了命想活下去一样
Maybe because I'll be dying first.
也许是因为我更接近死亡吧
No,
不
it's because you're trying to stay alive.
是因为你也拼了命想活下去
Isn't that so?
不是吗？
Well said.
说得好
You almost made me feel better.
差点就让我好起来了
Mr. Naruse, you've gotten hold of a Platinum Card.
成濑先生 你已经手握一张白金卡了
That's me.
那就是我
I'm your exclusive medical specialist.
我就是你的专属医生
Youngster, my exclusive specialist.
小伙子当我的专属医生啊
That's concerning.
有点担心呢
Why do you keep calling me that?
你干嘛一直叫我小伙子啊？
You've got a baby face.
你就青春洋溢的样子啊
A little youngster. Dr. Youngster.
就是小伙子嘛 小伙子医生
Old Man.
大叔
Shut up!
闭嘴
-Ms. Kanda. -Yes?
-菅田小姐 -是
I saw what happened.
我都看到了
REPORT ALL MEDICATION THAT IS TAKEN OUT
（取出药物后 务必填写医疗用品管理纪录）
POTASSIUM
（钾注射液）
That seemed like potassium to me.
他拿走的是钾注射液吧？
Mr. Yoshioka,
吉冈医生
don't tell anyone.
这件事不要告诉任何人
So pretty.
好美喔
-Hey, what's that? -Don't worry about it.
-那是什么啊？ -没什么 走吧
That sausage was delicious.
那香肠真的很好吃呢
Let me tell you the most delicious thing I've ever eaten.
那是我活到现在 吃过的最美味的东西喔
When I was in university,
是我念大学的时候去露营
I was camping out in nature
在空气清新的大自然中
and cooked a sausage over charcoal.
吃的炭烤香肠
That's youth.
青春的味道啊
I'm still not sure where I want to go,
我还没想到要去哪
but let's stay here for a minute.
暂时先待在这里吧
Okay.
好
You must like it here?
你喜欢这个地方吗？
Yes.
喜欢
It's just that…
只是…
I'm a bit scared.
有点害怕
Huh?
什么？
For years now,
那么多年以来
I've been in and out of the hospital,
我一直出入医院
and I think I've spent more time inside it now.
大部分时间都在医院里
I'll be discharged soon, and that's great,
能出院当然很高兴 但是啊
but without a nurse,
没有护士在身边
I feel helpless.
心里总是不踏实
I understand.
原来如此
I'm scared
我感到害怕
because this isn't a hospital.
是因为这里不是医院
-Mr. Naruse. -No,
-成濑先生 -不过
it's not that I want to go back.
我并不是说我想回去
Right.
是
I'm just a coward.
我只是个胆小鬼罢了
Two vials of 20cc potassium.
两瓶20cc的钾注射液？
Yes.
是的
Dr. Sakura.
佐仓吗？
We're missing two potassium vials.
少了两瓶钾注射液呢
I accidentally dropped them,
我不小心弄掉了
but I submitted a breakage report.
但我有提交破损报告了
I gave the breakage report to the head nurse
我交了破损报告给护理长
and tried to cover it up the best I could.
想办法掩盖过去了
I see.
这样啊
I understand.
我明白
so, don't mention it.
所以别再提了
Don't say anything.
就当作没这回事
Okay.
好
I know.
我知道了
Just don't say anything.
什么都不用说
Don't rich people
那个啊 有钱人
go to Switzerland or something?
不都会去瑞士什么的吗？
Huh?
什么？
For euthanasia.
安乐死
As of now,
现在
several other countries recognize the practice too.
有好几个国家也通过安乐死合法化了
For people who really can't live on,
对于那些实在活不下去的人
several places accept it,
就算没有预期寿命的证明
even without proof of life expectancy.
也有地方可以合法执行
I see.
这样啊
But in places like Switzerland,
但在瑞士的话
doesn't the doctor make the final judgment?
需要医生来做出最后的判断吧？
Thank you very much. I'll enjoy this.
谢谢 我不客气了
Thank you.
我不客气了
Yes, there are several regulations
是的 还是有一些规定
to determine
用来评估
whether euthanasia is appropriate.
是否符合资格接受安乐死
That's strange.
真是不可思议
If I was given the option of euthanasia,
要是我能选择安乐死的话
I'd be relieved,
一定会感觉如释重负
but it'll still be a little shocking.
但这样听起来还是有点难以接受
Huh?
什么？
I'm wondering if I'm doing that poorly,
我会想我是不是真的那么糟糕
objectively speaking.
客观来说的话
I understand.
我好像懂你的意思
Really.
是吗？
-You understand? -Yes.
-你懂？ -嗯
Although you want to die,
虽然自己一心求死
you want someone to say it's not that bad.
但还是希望有人对自己说
You want someone to tell you to just hang on.
情况没那么糟糕 可以再坚持看看
Isn't that right?
大概是这个意思吧？
I suppose so.
算是吧
-Don't push yourself. -Okay.
-不要硬撑喔 -好
Let's eat.
我要开动了
This is the magic potion number one.
这是魔法药水一号
And magic potion number two.
而这瓶是魔法药水二号
The first will kill you.
一号是致死的药物
It will let you immediately go to rest.
能够让人立刻解脱
The second will comfort you for a short while.
二号能让人暂时脱离痛苦
It's a powerful painkiller.
是一种强效的止痛药
Is this…
就是这两瓶啊？
These are…
这些药…
scary.
真可怕
I was longing for them.
是渴望已久的东西呢
You can use them when you want.
你随时都能使用
The ingredients to peace.
是能得到安息的工具
I can choose to live or die.
生或死都能自己选择
If we have the right to live, shouldn't we have the right to die?
人有权利活着 应该也有权利死亡吧？
No.
不对
Or is living our duty?
活着只是一个义务吧？
A room deep in the hospital ward,
躺在医院深处的一间病房里
being unable to eat alone,
连自己吃饭都做不到
and a body full of tubes,
全身插满管子
only feeding tubes, and never getting up,
只能依靠喂食管进食 卧床不起
and only wearing a diaper.
穿着尿不湿过日子
Do I really want to live for that?
真的不惜这样也要活下去吗？
Is that what everyone wants?
那是患者本人的意愿吗？
No, I'm not sure.
不 我也不确定
Doctors live to save people.
医生的职责是拯救生命
But I…
可是 我觉得
think that may be abuse.
那样是在虐待患者
Ever since you were born, Mr. Naruse,
自从成濑先生你出生以来
medicine has evolved,
医学不断进步
and average life expectancy has increased.
人的平均预期寿命有所增加
Yet,
不过
does that really make people happy?
延长寿命真的就能让人幸福吗？
Well,
这个嘛
we die either way.
反正人都会死的
Whether it's by that magic potion
不管是使用魔法药水也好
or by nature.
自然死亡也罢
Mr. Naruse, aren't you a novelist?
不过 成濑先生 你不是小说家吗？
Not so much anymore.
现在已经不算是了
You're a writer,
既然是作家
so, you'll be leaving your work behind.
应该会留下作品吧？
Whether I leave those behind or not
无论我有没有留下作品
won't matter when I die.
人死了就都不重要了
Being born into this world is overwhelming.
出生在这世上太艰难了
May I touch this?
可以碰你吗？
This feeling is proof that I'm alive.
这种感觉是我还活着的证明啊
If I die,
等我死了
I won't be able to touch it.
就不能再触摸了
-Mr. Naruse. -Call me Old Man.
-成濑先生 -叫我大叔吧
There's no future for me.
我已经没有未来了
I only have this time.
我只有现在
What are you doing, weirdo?
干嘛？恶心死了
People's bodies…
人的身体…
are quite warm.
很温暖呢
You're alive.
还活着喔
Both me and this old man.
我还活着 大叔你也是
What is he up to?
那家伙在搞什么啊？
What are you doing, Sakura?
你怎么了 佐仓？
Hey! Sakura!
喂 佐仓
Hey! Wake up!
喂！起床！
Wake up! It's coming!
快起床 来了…
Even the steam from this coffee you've made
连小伙子医生煮的咖啡冒出来的蒸汽
is once in a lifetime.
也是难能可贵的呢
I don't know if it'll taste good.
不知道好不好喝耶
It's good.
好喝
But why you?
但为什么是你呢？
What do you mean?
你这什么意思啊？
You're not a pretty girl or anything.
如果是漂亮的小姐就好了
That'd be nice for my last vacation.
毕竟是我人生最后一趟旅程
Don't expect too much. I'll go home.
不准要求那么多 不然我回家啰
Don't say all that. It was a joke.
别这样嘛 我只是开个玩笑啊
This world is beautiful.
这世界真美啊
Now that I'm facing death,
一想到人生来到了终点
this world doesn't seem so bad anymore.
这世界看上去也美多了呢
It's beautiful.
真的好美
Am I seeing things through a filter?
我的眼睛是不是开滤镜了？
No.
不是
This world is simply beautiful.
这世界的确很美
The sky above,
天空
the clouds, even the scent…
云朵 还有这气息…
are all part of this world.
都是这世界的一部分
Yes.
是的
I can't enjoy it once I die.
死了就感受不到了
That's true.
没错
Should I enjoy all the beauty before I die?
不如感受完这世界的美好再死吧
Huh?
什么？
I'd like to relive my life again.
我想再过一次自己的人生
This right here is where my memories are.
这里 我脑袋里的那些回忆
I want to live them out again.
我好想重温一遍
ROBINSON 771
（罗宾逊771）
Where are you from, Old Man?
大叔 你是哪里人啊？
Far, far out that way.
好远好远的地方
I swear it was around here.
明明是在这附近的啊
Things have changed a lot.
这地方变了不少呢
This used to be a bookstore, but now, it's karaoke.
这里以前是书店 现在是卡拉OK了
You don't know where your own house was?
你连自己的家在哪都不知道吗？
Our place was big.
我家可是很大的
It was a brewery from the Meiji period.
是明治时代开业的酿酒厂
We were well-known around here.
在这附近可是小有名气的
We owned the land.
我们是地主
This entire area was where my house used to be.
这一带以前都是我家的产业
There must have been some land readjustment.
肯定是重新规划过了吧
Huh?
咦？
Even the middle school,
连中学也不一样了
it's been rebuilt.
看来重建过了呢
It seems so. It's been decades.
也对 毕竟都几十年了
Hello!
你们好
I'm an alum.
我是你们的学长
-Is that so? -Yes.
-真的吗？ -是啊
-Do your best! -Thank you!
-要加油喔 -谢谢
That's okay. I'll take that.
没关系 我来拿
Thank you!
谢谢
-Good work today. -Yes.
-辛苦了 -是
Welcome back.
欢迎回来
The stars are beautiful.
星星好漂亮啊
Isn't this great?
这也太棒了吧
Huh?
咦？
There's even a bar counter!
连吧台都有啊
Old man, there's a bar counter--
大叔 这里面有吧台…
Old man. Old man!
大叔…
Old Man, are you okay?
大叔 你还好吗？
Just a bit…
再忍一下…
Just wait a bit longer.
再忍一下就好
We last used painkillers at five, so, we have to wait three hours.
最后一次用止痛药是在五点 得等到八点才能再用药
These hours feel so long.
这段时间太漫长了
It's like a vortex of pain.
感觉痛苦没完没了
I don't know just how much it hurts,
我感受不到你的痛苦
but I'm with you.
但我会陪着你
Why?
为什么？
Because I'm free?
因为我太闲了
That's great.
好好喔
This is your way of killing time?
你就这样看着我打发时间啊？
Oh, you can see the moon!
这里看得到月亮耶
I can't even move.
我连动都动不了
I guess so.
也对喔
Ouch.
好痛
I can't eat natto.
我没办法吃纳豆呢
Who cares?
干我屁事啊？
I mean…
不是 我只是想随便说点什么
I thought I should say something.
分散一下注意力
PENTAZOCINE
（喷他佐辛）
It's time. Eight o'clock.
可以了 八点了
This has pentazocine and hydroxyzine in it.
这注射液里面有喷他佐辛和羟嗪
Customized just for me.
为我量身调制的吗？
Like going to Starbucks.
就像在星巴克一样呢
Give me the usual…
我要平时点的那个…
Is it working?
起效了吧？
How did you know?
你怎么知道？
You've stopped tensing your shoulders, Old Man.
因为你的肩膀放松下来了 大叔
Customization, success.
量身调制 成功了
If you're feeling well tomorrow,
如果你明天有精神的话
let's go to the high school.
我们一起去高中吧
The one you went to.
你以前上的那所高中
I…
可是…
don't even know if it's there.
都不知道学校还在不在呢
I already checked.
我查过了
The school closed down three years ago,
那所高中三年前已经废校了
but the building is still there.
但那栋建筑还在
First to five wins.
先拿五分的获胜喔
-Here I come. -Okay.
-我要来啰 -好
Hey!
喂！
That's crazy.
差一点
Here I go!
我要来啰
Come at me!
来吧
-Ah, sorry! -Wait a minute.
-抱歉 -怎么这样？
That was way too good. No way.
这太厉害了吧 不可能啊
Try me.
来啊
I missed.
没进
So close.
差一点呢
The sky makes a good ceiling.
天空真是不错的天花板啊
Huh? A ceiling?
天空是天花板？
I'm sick of the hospital ceiling.
医院的天花板我都看腻了
I just get moved around
即便从一间病房转去另一间病房
from one white ceiling to another.
也全都是白色的天花板
Speaking of which, don't you have a home?
话说回来 你家里没问题吗？
Huh?
什么？
You've just been out with me.
你这样陪我出来旅行没问题吗？
I've got a broken family.
我离婚了
What?
什么？
More importantly, what was your youth like?
别说这个了 说说你的青春故事吧
I was a soccer player.
我年轻的时候是名足球员
I played in the inter-high league.
参加过高校总体大会
Kimura Kazushi was my rival.
对手是木村和司
What? Seriously?
什么？真的假的？
Really?
真的啊？
-You're way too gullible. -Huh?
-你真的太容易上当啦 -什么？
Of course I'm lying.
当然是骗你的啊
Damn…
真是的
Huh, what…
咦？等等
But were you lying about living here and being rich?
那你说自己老家在这里 而且是有钱人家 也是骗我的吗？
Pretty much.
是吧
Listen, if you were going to die,
我说啊 人生都要结束了
would it even matter what's truth or lie?
是真是假都不重要了吧？
I lied a little, creating a life that I wish I had.
我只是想过一过这样的人生 所以编造了一下
Right.
好吧
The truth about me
我真实的青春
was that I worked at a brewery,
是在酿酒厂度过的
all through middle and high school,
从中学到高中都在那里打工
doing nothing else.
没做别的了
I wish I played soccer.
要是当时有踢足球就好了
Oh, look.
哦 就是那家
-Hello. -Please come in!
-你好 -欢迎光临
What is this?
这是怎么回事啊？
I got a phone call from him,
他打电话给我啊
so, I thought why not, and invited him.
我就想说邀请他一起来嘛
Looks good.
好了
I'm excited.
不错喔…
Time for some beer.
来点啤酒吧
One beer coming up.
-一瓶啤酒？ -是的
-And for you? -The same.
-您呢？ -一样
Okay.
好的 您呢？
-Three, please. -Three beers!
-三瓶啤酒
KUSHIAGE
（串炸）
-Cheers.
-干杯
So good.
赞啦
Dr. Sakura, you don't pick up your phone.
佐仓医生 你都不接电话
I saw Mr. Naruse's clinical records,
所以我去翻了成濑先生的病历纪录
and I was worried.
我有点担心
But I never thought
不过没想到
you'd both be traveling all the way out here.
你们俩居然来到那么远的地方啊
You told him everything, huh?
你什么都告诉他了吧？
We're following our life paths.
这是一段追寻自己人生的旅程
-Your life paths? -Yes.
-追寻人生的旅程？ -没错
When you're about to die, you lose all sense of time.
将死之人已经不太能感知时间了
There's no difference whether you're 18 or 45.
无论是18岁还是45岁发生的事
It all feels the same.
回想起来感觉都一样
And it's full of memories.
全都是一段回忆
Today will be nothing but a memory tomorrow.
今天也一样 到了明天就变成回忆了
It sounds sad.
听起来有点伤感呢
Despite how I may seem,
别看我这样
I've achieved everything.
我可是什么成就都有了
I became a writer.
我当上了作家
I won awards. I was a hit.
还得过奖 作品很受欢迎
I'm dead broke now, though.
只是现在钱都花光了
If I must say,
真要说的话
I have no memories of youth.
我的青春没有留下回忆
That's my biggest regret.
这是我最大的遗憾
Memories of youth…
青春的回忆啊
Would you like something?
需要点什么吗？
Oh, no.
不用
Hey, wait!
诶 你…
Naruse…
成濑？
Aren't you Naruse?
你是成濑吧？
Yes.
是的
I'm dying.
我快死了
Perhaps you drank too much.
应该是喝太多了吧
I have good medicine for that.
我带了很有效的药来
-Let's have him take it. -Okay.
-让他试试吧 -好
Hey, don't tell Nakano.
诶 不准告诉中野
What?
什么？
Don't tell Yuri.
不要告诉百合
Your old schoolmate?
你的高中学妹？
Did you like her?
难道你喜欢过她？
Ouch, ouch.
痛…
You're doing that on purpose.
你这是演的吧？
No, it hurts!
不是啦 真的很痛
I brought Wuling San Wan.
这是五苓散
-Want to try? -No.
-要试试看吗？ -不要
-Take it. -Fine.
-试试看啊 -好吧
Seriously.
真是的
I don't want to die.
我不想死
I don't want to die, Doctor.
我还不想死啊 医生
Only in times like this
只有这种时候
do you call me doctor.
你才会叫我医生
I feel like if I call you that, you can do something for me.
我想说叫你医生的话 你应该会做点什么吧
I also feel like I have to do something.
我也觉得我得做点什么
Sometimes I say I want to die,
我一时说想死
and I also say that I want to live.
一时说想活下去
I'm so weird.
真奇怪呢
Aren't all humans that way?
人不都这样吗？
That's what they all say.
那都是嘴上说说而已
As if it were a movie.
就像电影那样
Huh?
什么？
I know because I'm a writer.
我是作家 所以我很清楚
Stories are far too happy.
编造的故事往往都很动听
That's why…
所以…
they're beautiful.
很美好
Death itself is indescribable. Because you're dead.
死亡本身是无法形容的 毕竟人都死了
That's why
所以…
the people around us,
死亡…
who are alive, tell the stories.
都是由还活着的人来诉说的
Beautifully.
说得很美好
I suppose you're right.
也对
You can't know a person's feelings.
他们又怎么知道将死之人的心情呢？
In the movies,
在电影里面看到的
things wrap up nicely.
人生的最后都很圆满
Their ashes
死去的人的骨灰
are scattered on Mt. Fuji or Mt. Everest,
会被撒在富士山 还是珠穆朗玛峰之类的
and the movie ends.
接着电影结束
The characters only fear death,
里面的人物害怕死亡
feel pain, and suffer for five seconds,
感受痛苦的时间不过才五秒
then the scene ends.
然后那一幕就拍完了
But in real life, it's much longer.
但在现实生活中 这段过程漫长多了
It feels so long I could die.
漫长到我都快死了
There's no end to it.
感觉没有尽头
What is that?
什么啊？
My mom used to sing it.
我妈妈常唱这首歌
Oh.
哦
I know that too.
我听过耶
It's Yuming.
是松任谷由实的歌
It hurts, but I can laugh.
好痛 但我还笑得出来
I'm scared, but I laugh.
好害怕 但我还笑得出来
I can forget it all for a moment.
暂时忘掉死亡了
Yes.
是
There are so many forms of time.
时间有很多种形式呢
There's a moment.
有一瞬间
Perhaps a collection of moments is what we call life.
或许就是很多个瞬间 组成了所谓的人生吧
KOZUYU
（小汁）
Here you go.
来
Thank you very much.
谢谢你
It looks great.
看起来好好吃
I didn't know.
是这样啊
Who'd think his condition was that bad.
没想到他的身体状况那么糟
I wanted to bring him today too,
我今天原本想带他一起来的
but his condition wasn't great.
但他的情况不太好
Hey, what about the hospital?
我说啊 医院那边没问题吗？
I'll go back tomorrow morning.
我明天早上回去
Were you let go?
你被开除了？
No.
没有
I was a student library assistant.
我以前是图书馆管理员
I can somewhat tell.
可以看得出来呢
-Please take these. -Okay.
-麻烦你了 -好
OEDIPUS THE KING
（《伊底帕斯王》）
You must like reading.
你一定很喜欢阅读吧
I'm a writer. Occasionally.
我有时候会写点东西
Really?
真的啊？
Yes.
嗯
Would you like to read my work?
你要读读看我写的故事吗？
Of course.
好啊
Thank you.
太好了
It never happened, though.
但他也没给我看过什么
He was all talk.
只会空口说白话
Hey…
那个…
I have a favor to ask.
我有个请求
For bringing back memories of his youth.
希望能勾起他的青春回忆
POTASSIUM
（钾注射液）
What are you looking for?
你在找什么？
What do you want to take?
你想拿走什么？
POTASSIUM
（钾注射液）
This.
这个
Did the higher-ups tell you to?
是你上级的指示吗？
No.
不是
It's my decision.
是我自己的决定
Can't you leave it here?
不拿走不行吗？
It was given to me as a charm.
这是他给我的护身符
A charm?
护身符？
Only because…
就是因为有这个
I have that am I able to live.
我才能活到现在
My journey can continue.
我的旅程才能继续
Do you understand me?
你明白我的心情吗？
I'm completely terrified.
恐惧在吞噬着我
Please don't take it from me.
拜托你不要拿走
I saw nothing.
我什么都没看到
Let's leave it at that.
就这样放着吧
It's freezing.
好冷喔
Yes.
是啊
So,
所以
what are you here for?
你是来干嘛的？
Well, that's fine.
没关系吧
Yes?
那个…
I can't explain it well.
我也说不清楚
What?
什么事？
The day before last,
前天
I heard you and Mr. Naruse's conversation.
我听到你跟成濑先生的对话
It made me realize something.
让我理解了一件事
What's this about?
说什么呢？
You want to save him,
你很想救他
but you can't,
但却无能为力
so, you just stay by his side
所以你只想陪在他身边
and talk with him.
跟他聊聊天
It reminded me of being a kid.
让我想起了小时候
What's up with that?
干嘛突然说这些？
We…
我们…
I mean, I don't mean to speak for you,
抱歉 把你也含括在一起
but we are humans before we are doctors.
在医生这个身分之前 我们是人
We're human.
大家都是人
Doctors and patients,
医生和患者
we're all human.
不过都是血肉之躯
EXIT
（出口）
Naruse!
成濑
Come on. What are you doing?
拜托 你在干嘛啦？
Come on.
过来啦
Quickly.
快点
Naruse!
成濑
Yo.
嗨
Let's go.
走吧
It's the music room.
是音乐室
Do you remember?
你还记得吗？
If I remember, behind this door…
我没记错的话 这扇门后面…
Look, it's still there!
你看 还在呢
I WANT TO BECOME A NOVELIST - NARUSE I WANT TO BE A DESIGNER IN TOKYO - NAKANO
（成濑翔：我要当小说家 中野百合：我要去东京当设计师）
I remember us messing around here,
我还记得我们俩像电视剧那样
like we were in a drama.
在这里混了不少时间呢
Here.
给
Right here.
这边
Okay.
好
Go to Tokyo…
我要去东京…
So embarrassing.
好难为情啊
I heard fireworks.
是烟花的声音吧
Everyone
大家…
must have forgotten by now.
应该都忘记了吧
Huh?
什么？
Once I die…
等我死了…
Hey, Old Man.
大叔
Didn't you forget until Yuri told you?
要不是百合小姐告诉你的话 你不也忘记了吗？
You just remembered now.
你也是刚刚才想起来啊
Honestly, I still can't remember.
老实说 我还是没想起来
I'm still wondering if it happened.
我还在想有没有这件事
I mean, why the music room--
-是说 为什么音乐室… -大叔
Old men like you usually live 22,000 days.
像大叔你这年纪的人 已经活了两万两千天了
It's only natural to forget a few.
有想不起来的事也很正常
But something this important…
但这么重要的事…
It makes me think.
是说啊
People only remember the good times.
人都只记得开心的事
My memories might be broken up.
我的过去搞不好很悲惨
I think your life
我倒觉得
has been even better than you remember.
你的人生比你记得的还要更美好呢
You've just forgotten.
你只是忘了
That sounds nice.
听起来不错喔
People don't usually prepare so thoroughly to die.
不过 一般人通常都没机会 为死亡准备得那么充分吧
Lots of people die
大部分人
despite having plans for the next day.
都是想好明天要做什么 今天却挂掉了
That's true.
说的也是
But that's just
但那只是
one of the many ways to die.
其中一种死法罢了
-I found a great spot. -Huh?
-我找到了一个好地方 -是吗？
For a picnic. A rooftop picnic.
野餐 屋顶野餐
A nighttime rooftop picnic.
夜空下的屋顶野餐
I'm having so much fun.
真的好开心呢
How amazing.
好厉害喔
And with fireworks included.
而且还能看烟花
Well then, I'll sit here.
好 那我去那边
-If anything happens… -What?
-有事的话… -咦？
Hey!
喂
-Doctor, take this. -Hey!
-医生 这个 -喂
Well, that's fine.
算了吧
What's this?
这是什么？
Am I supposed to do this?
这样可以吗？
Yes, just like that.
嗯 可以
It hasn't changed at all.
一点也没变呢
There's no reason it shouldn't.
物是人非了啊
How should I say?
怎么说呢？
Neither has your laugh.
你的笑还是一样
Did we always have winter fireworks?
以前也有冬季烟花大会吗？
I think it started seven years ago.
大概是七年前开始的吧
For tourism or something.
宣传观光之类的
Mama!
妈妈
Mom, come here!
妈妈 来这边
Okay!
好
Wow, look at this.
看这个…
Look, look.
你看…
Look this way!
看这边
Look at the camera.
看镜头
Smile.
笑一个
Oh, it finished!
烧完了
I've lost…
全都…
everything.
没了啊
Thank you for coming.
你竟然回来了呢
I didn't expect you to be here.
我没想到你会在这
I moved around a bit after getting married,
结婚之后 我曾经搬去其他城市
but I came back.
但最后还是回来了
I wonder how many years it's been.
多少年过去了啊
Do you have kids?
有小孩吗？
I couldn't.
我不能生小孩
That may be why I got divorced.
这或许…是我离婚的原因吧
Oh, it looks like a heart!
是心型的耶
There are so many now.
现在什么形状都有呢
There are.
是啊
Hey,
诶
you never showed me what you wrote in high school.
你都没给我看过 你高中的时候写的故事呢
Is your book finished?
你的小说写完了吗？
-Not yet. -Not yet?
-还没 -还没？
I've just got a bit more left.
还剩一点 快写完了
Do your best.
加油喔
I never finished it.
那个到现在还是未完成品呢
But I still read it.
但我一直有在读喔
Since you became a pro.
自从你正式出书以来
You've been amazing, a real novelist.
你好厉害啊 真的当上小说家了
Not at all.
还好啦
Naruse?
成濑？
-Who are you calling? -Doctor Sakura.
-你要找谁？ -佐仓医生
-Hang on. -What?
-等一下 -什么？
Could we stay together a bit longer?
不能一起多待一会吗？
I just called.
打通了耶
Really?
不是吧？
Hang on.
等一下
I liked you.
我高中时很喜欢你
Really?
真的吗？
Me too.
我也是
What?
什么？
I could never work up the courage to say it.
我始终没能鼓起勇气跟你表白
Naruse.
成濑
He must have said something.
那家伙肯定说了
Even though I told him not to.
我明明不准他说的
Old Man, are you okay?
大叔 你还好吗？
You…
你…
Naruse, you're wrong!
成濑 你搞错了
I've applied a stabilizer and sedative,
我施打了稳定剂和镇静剂
so, he should be resting for a bit.
休息一下就好了
Um…
那个…
Yes?
嗯？
What is it?
什么事？
Are you stupid?
你是傻子吗？
Oh, I'm sorry!
抱歉
But we'd be worried without you.
但你不在的话 会有点不安
No, he'll be fine.
不…他不会有事的
Let me know if anything happens.
有事再叫我吧
I'm going out to smoke…
我去外面…
I don't smoke.
抽根…我不抽烟耶
I've got some work to do.
我去做点事
Naruse.
成濑
What?
是
You're wrong.
你搞错了
It's not because you're dying.
不是因为你快死了
I really liked you.
我是真的喜欢你
Don't say I'm going to die.
别提我快死掉这件事嘛
Sorry.
抱歉
Although it's true.
不过也是事实啦
Can I touch your face?
我可以摸摸你的脸吗？
That's…
这…
Does it hurt?
你的脸会痛吗？
My face doesn't hurt.
我的脸不痛
Then…
那…
I just now did what I couldn't back then.
我刚做的是我以前没能做的事
I'm no longer a high school student.
我已经不是高中生了
I'm no longer young.
也不年轻了
Sorry about that.
抱歉喔
Idiot.
傻瓜
-Okay. -Oh.
-喂？ -哦
Oh, you're alive.
你还活着啊？
Yes, I'm alive.
还活着
I threw out your resignation letter.
我把你的离职信丢掉了
You're coming back.
你要回来喔
Huh?
什么？
I'm not coming back.
我不会回去的
I believe you.
我相信你
What do you mean?
相信我什么？
That I'll go back to forcing patients to live?
相信我会回去强迫患者活下去吗？
I…
我…
that the last three months of my mother's life
我怎么想都不认同
were needed for her at all.
我母亲临终前那三个月 是她的人生必须经历的日子
We were just delaying the inevitable.
我们只是在拖延死亡而已
What did she do for those three months?
那三个月她都做什么了？
She only suffered.
不过是在受苦罢了
The doctors did nothing for her!
医生根本束手无策
Aren't humans
人类啊
so greedy to keep reproducing?
真是想尽一切办法去繁衍后代呢
We have infertility treatment,
不孕症治疗
egg cryopreservation,
卵子冷冻
and sperm banks.
还有精子银行
When it comes to giving birth,
要生小孩的时候
we do so much that defies God's will.
人类可以不惜违背神的旨意
And yet,
然而
why must it all end in death?
为什么要死的时候就不可以呢？
As if He pretends not to see.
彷佛神会假装看不见似的
Giving birth is more interesting.
生小孩的乐趣比较多吧
May I hang up?
我可以把电话挂掉了吗？
Listen, Sakura.
听好了 佐仓
Doctors save people's lives.
医生的职责是拯救生命
That is our duty.
这是我们的使命
You're wrong.
不是这样的
I want to save their view of life.
我想拯救的是患者的人生
Is that why you brought the potassium?
所以你才会把钾注射液带走？
Are you a God?
你是神吗？
Choosing whether people live or die
一个人是生是死
is not your right to decide.
由不得你去决定
Nobody has that right.
任谁都没权利做这个决定
But there is no God!
但这世界没有神啊
There is no God…
这世界没有神
so, I must do it.
所以就由我来做
Sakura.
佐仓
Don't persevere too much.
不要那么固执
Don't become too soft.
也不要太心软
I'm worried about you.
我很担心你
Hey…
那个…
-Yes? -Naruse needs you.
-是 -成濑他…
I'll be right there.
我马上过去
Sorry, I have to hang up.
抱歉 我先挂了
It's okay. He's alive.
没事 他还活着
The medicine makes people sleepy.
那药物会让人昏昏欲睡
I see.
原来如此
I see…
好了
Here.
给
Oh, thank you.
谢谢
Will you be back tomorrow?
你明天会过来吗？
He said to stop.
他说到此为止了
He said this would be the last time.
还说以后别再见面了
Old Man said that? Oh, I mean, Mr. Naruse said that?
咦？大叔说的？成濑先生说的吗？
He wanted to keep things beautiful.
他想要让回忆停留在美好的时刻
He wanted me to remember him that way.
想要我记得他那副模样
He didn't want to show me when he's weak.
不想让我看到他虚弱的样子
It's so like him.
他就是这样的人
I'll be off.
我走了
-Be safe. -Thank you.
-路上小心 -谢谢
Old Man.
大叔
Please let me die. Please.
让我死吧 求你了
-What? -I've…
-什么？ -我…
I've had enough.
我已经满足了
I've had this strange adventure with you
跟你经历了这段奇妙的旅程
and remembered my youth.
回顾了我的青春
Now, let me die.
现在 可以让我死了
I understand.
我知道了
I don't want to.
不要
I don't want
大叔
-you to die. -What?
-我不要你死 -什么？
I want to talk to you again tomorrow.
我明天还想跟你聊天
I want to see your smiling face.
还想看到你的笑容
You don't even need to smile.
你不想笑也没关系
You can even sleep.
睡一整天也可以
I don't want you to leave this world.
我不要你离开这个世界
What are you talking about?
你在说什么啊？
That's your ego talking.
你这是在自说自话吧
Just as you always say,
正如你平时常说的
I don't want to be full of tubes
我不想全身插满管子
and be forced to stay alive.
被迫活下去
Fine, it's my ego.
就当我是在自说自话吧
I just don't want you to die.
我就是不要你死
I like being with you.
我真的好喜欢你啊
Gross!
有够恶心的啦！
That hurts!
好痛！
Why…
为什么嘛？
Why must the dying person's feelings come before mine?
为什么非得要我 优先考虑临终的人的心情呢？
I have feelings too.
我也有感情的
The person you leave has feelings too.
被留下来的人也有感情的
It's my illness.
生病的是我
It's my life!
这条命也是我的
Even so…
即便如此…
would you live for me instead?
大叔 你就当作是 为了我活下去 不行吗？
At least until tomorrow?
至少活到明天？
If I must.
真拿你没办法啊
If Dr. Youngster wants it that bad…
既然小伙子医生都开口了…
I'll eventually die anyway, so, no rush.
反正我早晚都得死
I already suffered today anyway.
而且今天已经熬过去了
I'll live another day.
就再撑一天吧
When tomorrow comes, your mood will change.
等到明天 你的想法会改变的
I don't care!
屁啦！
It hurts.
好痛…
Three hours haven't passed yet.
三个小时还没过去呢
You devil.
你这个魔鬼
I suppose you're right.
说的也是啊
Humans live not just for themselves
人活着不是只为了自己
but for others as well.
或许也为了别人吧
If it were only for themselves,
要是只为自己而活
it'd be quite dull.
人生也满无聊的 是吧？
You can sleep great after all that.
大闹一场之后还睡得那么好喔
Saying you'd be left behind…
被留下来的人啊…
The sea?
看海？
Yes.
嗯
I want to see
我想…
the sea again.
再看一次大海
The Torii at the sea…
海中央有鸟居…
Daddy!
爸爸
Look!
你看
Wait, wait.
等等…
Chihiro, don't go.
千寻 待在这边
I won't.
别过去
I got it!
爸爸拿到了
I had a daughter.
我有一个女儿
Really?
什么？
My wife died,
我老婆死了以后
and I haven't seen her since.
我就再也没见过她了
I haven't seen
我已经几十年…
my daughter for decades.
没见过我女儿了
Where is she?
她在哪？
Old Man!
大叔
Let's go!
我们走吧 去这个地方
Shouldn't the final destination for our journey be right here?
这是我们这趟旅程的 最后一个目的地吧？
Miyagi Prefecture, Sendai City.
宫城县 仙台市
NARUSE CHIHIRO MIYAGI SENDAI
（成濑翔先生收 寄信人地址：宫城县仙台市）
Are you okay?
你还好吧？
I've become light.
我一定变轻了吧
-Your weight? -No.
-体重吗？ -不是
The weight of my life has decreased.
是我生命的重量
It should be around here.
应该在这附近了
NO BIKING
（禁止骑自行车）
Huh?
怎么了？
-That's her. -Huh?
-是她 -什么？
That's Chihiro.
是千寻
She seems happy.
她看起来好幸福
That's good. That's enough.
很好 这样就够了
Mrs. Chihiro.
千寻小姐
I'm sorry.
对不起
Old Man. Old Man!
大叔…
We've come this far.
我们都大老远过来了
Please come in.
欢迎光临
Sorry, my house was a mess, so…
抱歉 我家有点乱…
Well, I'll be out for a walk.
好 那我去走走啰
Do you want something to drink?
你要喝点什么吗？
Some coffee.
咖啡吧
Excuse me. One more coffee.
不好意思 麻烦再来一杯咖啡
Okay, got it!
好的
I've gotten old, haven't I?
我变老了吧？
I don't remember the past that well.
小时候的事我也记不清
I see.
这样啊
You've gotten bigger.
你长大了呢
Bigger, but…
说我长大了…
I'm over 30 years old.
我都三十多岁了
You didn't come to Mom's funeral.
你没有来妈妈的告别式吧
I'm sorry.
抱歉
It's almost her seventh anniversary.
快满七年了
I didn't know if I had the right to go.
我不知道我有没有资格去
And I didn't know anything until I heard about her death.
而且 她去世了之后 我才知道她的情况
But when I go to Heaven,
不过 等我上去了
I'll apologize to her.
我会好好向她道歉的
Huh?
什么？
I mean,
我是说
I'm going to die too.
我也快死了
Thank you for waiting.
久等了
Thank you.
谢谢
That's right.
对了
I never wrote back to your New Year's card.
你寄来的贺年卡我都没回复过呢
It was just a generic one that I sent as a formality.
反正只是出于礼节寄送的一般贺卡
Is your marriage going well?
你的婚姻还顺利吗？
Sorry for being nosy.
是我多管闲事了
I was lonely after mom died, so, I got married.
妈妈去世后 我一个人很孤单 就去嫁人了
I see.
这样啊
But I'm happy.
但我很幸福
That's good.
那就好
Um…
那个…
Mom had a boyfriend.
妈妈有个男朋友喔
After you left,
你离开之后
she worked as a temporary employee,
她一边打临时工
as she built her own company.
一边开了自己的公司
It was a small company.
不过只是一家小公司
She did that, huh?
是吗？她开公司啦？
That's crazy.
好厉害啊
Her life completely changed, and I had no idea.
在我不知道的时候 她的人生都翻天覆地了啊
What?
什么？
What is it?
什么意思？
I was naive.
我好天真啊
I thought she would always think of me.
我还以为你妈妈一直想着我
Or so I thought.
放不下我呢
That's why
所以呢
she didn't call you until she died.
她临死前也一直没有联络你
I think Mom didn't want her boyfriend to find out.
我想妈妈是不想要那个男朋友知道吧
I see.
原来是这样
She loved him that much, huh?
她那么爱那个男人啊
I'm sorry for coming by.
抱歉 突然来找你
It'll be dinnertime soon.
要回去准备晚饭了吧？
Yes.
嗯
Don't think anything of it.
好了 没什么事啦
I thought I might write a book about this area,
我想说写一本关于这地方的故事
so…
所以…
you know,
那个…
I was just peeking around.
我才会过来四处看看
-See you. -I see.
-我走啰 -这样啊
Dad.
爸爸
Stay healthy.
你要保重身体喔
Yeah.
好
You too.
你也是
The medicine isn't working anymore.
药物已经不起作用了
Even an amateur like me can tell.
就算我不是医生 我也知道这点
Isn't it time for me to go?
这种时候可以走了吧？
It's hard and painful.
很难受、很痛苦
Please put me to rest…
让我解脱吧
with your magic potion.
你的魔法药水…
It's time.
是时候派上用场了
I understand.
我知道了
Thank you.
谢了
First, I'll administer Propofol.
首先 我会先注射丙泊酚
When I do, you will peacefully come to rest.
这样一来 你就能安详地陷入昏迷状态
PROPOFOL
（丙泊酚）
Why are there two?
怎么会有两瓶？
Are you…
难道说…
planning to die?
你打算自杀？
After I die,
我死去之后
are you planning to die too?
你也要死吗？
For what?
为什么？
It's true
没错
that I don't understand your bodily pain.
我无法体会患者生理上的痛楚
But…
可是…
my heart has come to hurt too.
我的心也很痛啊
My chest hurts. Ever since then.
从那时起 我的胸口一直很痛
Because you failed that operation?
因为那场手术失败了？
I didn't fail the operation!
那场手术没有失败
That was the rumor among the nurses.
护士们都在谣传这件事
Your mentor's operation.
你的恩师的手术
During your high school mentor's operation,
在为你的高中恩师动手术途中
your hand began to shake.
你的手开始颤抖
-Metzen. -Okay.
-组织剪刀 -是
Hey.
喂
What are you doing, Sakura?
你怎么了 佐仓？
Hey, Sakura!
喂 佐仓
-Replace him. -Yes, sir.
-换你来 -是
-Follow me.
-跟紧我
Tweezers.
镊子
Since then,
从那时起
I could never hold a scalpel again.
我再也无法拿起手术刀
And then,
后来
my wife left me.
我老婆就离我而去了
She didn't like me
她喜欢的不是我
but the genius surgeon that I once was.
而是曾经被称为 天才外科医生的那个我
She lost interest
当她看到
when I went to the department of psychosomatic medicine.
我被调去身心内科之后 就对我失去了兴趣
There was another man.
她在外面还有别的男人
That…
这一切…
is in your past.
都是你的过去
You have a future.
你还有未来
Live on.
活下去
You must live on.
活下去吧
The tomorrow you're throwing away
你想要抛弃的明天
is what another person would give an arm and a leg for.
可是某个将死之人 梦寐以求的美好日子啊
Live for me.
活下去吧
Why…
为什么？
Why do I have to live? Tell me!
为什么非要我活下去不可？你说啊！
Because you were born.
因为你生而为人了啊
You were born so you can live.
正因为你生而为人 才能好好活着啊
Exploring the past made my heart open up.
这段追寻过去的旅程敞开了我的心
I've lived until now.
我现在还活着
I…
我…
want to go to your hospital
要回去小伙子医生你任职的医院
and die under your care.
在你的照护下死去
Let's go back.
我们回去吧
What?
什么？
Until then,
回去之后
I will live until death.
我会一直活着 直到死去
Old Man.
大叔
THREE YEARS LATER
（三年后）
Pardon me.
我进去了
RELIEF CARE SPECIALIST TEAM
（安宁疗护医疗团队）
These are Mr. Tsukino and Mr. Akiyama's files.
这些是月野先生 还有秋山先生的病历纪录
Please return them by this weekend.
请在这周末之前归还
And with that, I'd like to continue the medication.
综上所述 我希望能维持现状 继续用药
Thank you very much.
谢谢大家
Her feelings have not once changed.
患者的想法一直没改变过
For the past month, she's wanted to be sedated.
过去这一个月以来 她一直想要镇静治疗
SEDATION: A SEDATIVE IS ADMINISTERED
（镇静：为了纾缓患者的痛苦）
TO PUT THE PATIENT UNCONSCIOUS FOR THEIR COMFORT
（持续使用镇静药物 令患者意识下降）
She's in pain every moment she's awake.
意识清醒的每分每秒 她都在承受着痛苦
Isn't it too early? What about her family?
现在说这个还太早了吧？ 她的家人没意见吗？
It can be appealed and puts the hospital at risk.
万一家属投诉 会给院方带来风险
It'd be scary.
后果不堪设想
Risk to the hospital?
给院方带来风险？
Who are we caring for?
我们的医疗服务对象是谁啊？
Who is the sedative for?
镇静治疗的对象是谁啊？
Why can't the patient decide how they go?
为什么不能让患者本身 决定自己的死亡方式呢？
Doctor.
佐仓医生
We'll never come to a resolution that way.
你再那样的话 事情永远不会有解决方案的
It got heated.
不小心激动过头了
Let's plan a strategy for the next conference.
下一次会议我们先制定好策略吧
Look who's talking.
居然得听你的啊
-Alright. -I'll have the fish.
-好 -我今天吃鱼吧
And it took two hours…
花了两小时…
I'm beat.
快累死了
At Relief Care, anybody can administer sedatives.
安宁疗护团队的人 只需要施打镇静剂 谁都做得到嘛
There's no technique needed.
根本不需要什么技术
The doctors are what makes them better.
能治好他们的是医生
What?
什么？
I think it's more difficult than the Batista operation.
是吗？我倒觉得 那比左心室部分切除手术还要困难
What?
什么？
It's not here,
不是这里
but here and here. You need a heart.
而是这里和这里 需要有一颗真心才行
You all could never do it.
你们这辈子都做不到…
Old Man, are you well?
大叔 你好吗？
I'm doing fine. I'm trying my best.
我很好 在尽力做好我的本分
I ended up moving to Relief Care.
回来之后 我转到安宁疗护医疗团队服务了
I still don't understand this field,
我还不是很理解这门领域
but I want to protect the patients' lives.
但我想守护患者的人生
I want to allow the patients to die peacefully.
我想让患者安详地离开人世
I don't want them to think, "I can finally leave this world behind."
我希望他们在临终时刻 想的不是“总算可以离开这世界了”
I want them to end their life thinking, "This world wasn't so bad after all."
而是“这世界还是满不错的”
Because this world isn't bad at all.
毕竟这世界还是满不错的 不是吗？
That's what you taught me.
那是大叔你教会我的
It was so good, those sausages.
真的很好吃呢 那时候的香肠
They were.
是的
When I die,
等我死了
it'll all be gone.
一切都会烟消云散
I'll remember you. I'll never forget.
我会记住的 永远不会忘记
Become a good doctor.
要当个好医生喔
Make more patients happy,
要让更多患者
just like me.
变得像我一样幸福
Don't cry.
别哭了
Dr. Youngster.
小伙子医生
Old Man.
大叔
Hang on. Just a bit more.
撑住啊 再撑一会
I called Mrs. Chihiro.
我叫千寻小姐来了
Old Man.
大叔
Old Man! Mrs. Chihiro is here.
大叔 千寻小姐来了
Dad.
爸爸
Dad, I wanted to introduce you to someone.
爸爸 我有个人想介绍给你认识
This is my son.
就是我的儿子
Kai.
小海
Grandpa.
外公
Look,
你看
he's your grandson.
是你的孙子喔
He's a boy,
明明是个男生
but he loves stuffed animals,
却很喜欢毛绒娃娃
and I gave him my favorite bunny.
我就把我最爱的毛绒兔子送他了
He's your grandpa.
他是你的外公
Dad.
爸爸
Old Man smiled for the last time.
那是大叔最后一次微笑
He shouldn't have been conscious, but I'm sure he smiled.
他应该已经没有意识了 但我肯定他笑了
It was the biggest smile I've ever seen.
是我看过最灿烂的笑容
It's still etched in my memory.
至今依旧铭刻在我心上
Your condition seems great.
你的身体状况很好呢
As long as
只要…
I'm still me,
我还是我
I can't become happy.
就无法变得幸福
This illness
毕竟这身病痛
has always been with me.
总是如影随形啊
That may be true.
或许是这样没错
But even if you can't become happy,
不过 即便你无法变得幸福
haven't you had moments of happiness?
应该也有过幸福的瞬间吧？
Don't you occasionally
应该也曾因为某人的笑话
laugh at people's jokes?
开怀大笑过吧？
When the weather is great,
天气晴朗的日子
doesn't your mood get a little better?
心情也会变得舒畅吧？
Look, that tea over there,
还有 那边的焙茶
didn't it taste good?
也有很好喝的时候吧？
Doctor.
医生
Do you ever feel glad that you're handsome?
你有没有想过 自己长得那么帅真是太好了？
Thanks.
好耶
Is happiness the goal?
幸福是一个目标吗？
I think it's more like
我认为幸福更像是活着的时候
a nice, rewarding breeze
偶尔感受到的
that you feel when you're alive.
像奖励一样的沁人心脾的微风
Doctor,
医生
I'm going to have a quick nap.
我想小睡一会
I'm falling asleep.
我困了
Speaking of which,
说起来
sleeping brings me happiness too.
入睡的瞬间也很幸福呢
Oh. Your sedative may be taking effect.
是喔 镇静剂起作用了呢
Doctor?
医生
Would you
你能不能…
hold my hand?
握着我的手？
Huh?
什么？
I mean, if you're okay with it.
可以啊 你不介意的话
It feels just like when my son was young,
感觉就像我儿子小时候的手一样呢
and my husband's hand,
也像已经过世很久的
who passed away long ago.
我丈夫的手
It feels like when I was young
也像我小时候牵过的…
and held my mother's hand.
我妈妈的手
I wish my hands were so perfect.
要是我有那么美好的双手就好了
Doctor…
医生
These are tears of joy.
这都是开心的眼泪
I know.
是的
Old Man, I am alive.
大叔 我还活着
Subtitle translation by: Nicolai Wacht
字幕翻译：蔡晓琳